soft engineer a do episode 124 OpenJDK
[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at s e - radio dotnet
I see radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every 10
days thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website for
support
[Music]
hi everybody welcome to another episode
of soft engineering radio this is Arno
and today I'm interviewing lollipop
topic from Sun Microsystems about open
JDK and open source in general tovo
would you like to start by saying a few
words about yourself yes hi arnhem and
hi everybody
necie radio I'm actually just started to
work at Sun Microsystems earlier this
year in April as their open source
ambassador basically for Java and my
involvement all this comes from years of
participating in projects like cafe
which is an open source virtual machine
and gnu classpath that have strived to
provide completely free implementations
of the java platform on many different
platforms so once Sun open up their code
they reached out to the existing
community outside Sun and so we started
working together and after a while of
that I decided to join the company and
help push things from the inside as well
okay so now you're working with open JDK
indeed open JDK is the open source
implementations of Java SE Sun has
actually done a bunch of those things in
the positive levels open up their
enterprise Java platform that's approach
a class efficient it also open up the
mobile platform which is the phone ami
project but SC is the one that most
people associate with Java so yeah
that's open JDK and that's where the
development of the next version takes
place on JDK 7 how long has this open
sourcing strategy been going on how did
it get started well earlier the earliest
attempts actually to have open source
java have begun almost as soon as Java
itself was published so historically the
earliest efforts like cafe bar
approaches I was associated with and gcj
date back to 1997 1996 that time frame
but sun has really only joined the fray
from 2005 onwards when sun actually
published the enterprise java platform
first on the CDL license and then
announced that I would actually be able
to opening up Java C itself and the
mobile implementation in 2006 at JavaOne
and since then they basically spent the
first year opening up their se source
code the mobile guys were done after six
months of course but the scope of the
mobile class libraries for example is
lot smaller whereas that act took the SE
guys around a year and unfortunately
because some of the components from 4se
came from third parties sun couldn't
actually open up all of those so there
was a small set of sub code encumbrances
that had to be replaced either by
reusing existing code from other
projects like the phonemic project for
example or by rewriting it from scratch
or bursting community contributions and
those parts where for example the font
rendering engine or for example the
sound engine so the sound engine section
component came out from the community
and was contributed by carl hagar son
got from eastland from iceland and that
was a great thing to have actually its
show but the project has potential to
attract massive producers from outside
what actually made mates what made Sango
open-source I mean why did they do that
Java was there to stay and the
commercial JVM was widely used why open
sources why go to all this trouble I
think there are a couple of aspects
there first of BAM was that open source
java say five years ago was a bit of a
scary thought for a lot of people
because they imagined that evil things
would happen everybody would come and
fork it and all that and after 10 years
of java being out there and you know
billions of lines of code written in
java language it's kind of unlikely that
somebody would actually successfully be
able to break the platform so I think a
watch part with motivation was that that
fear has gone away at the same time
the rise of say Linux and open source in
general has certainly helped justify
such a massive step because back in 96
when Java started out open-source was
wasn't even there it was all still
called free software back then of course
and the idea of openness for computing
for kokanee platform languages wasn't
that hot so that has changed massively
in the meantime you have whole
governments actually mandating open
source and open standards whereas before
it was purely open standards base so so
you're saying that opening Java opening
the JVM sort of helps success now
because more and more potential
customers see that as an asset Arizona
thrives and it's helps people and be
reasonably sure that the platform will
stay around for quite a while right
while at the same time allowing the kind
of freedom you would need to actually
have a platform evolve and put it into
the hands of the people who actually
want to use it and one of the niches
where Java wasn't around for a long time
as a part of say the core distribution
set is Linux and that's part of the
motivation as well because I'm the Linux
side of things for the longest time Java
has been seen as a proprietary platform
even though there was a solo piece in
its aspect just because then many
implementations were proprietary
themselves so accordingly opening up the
source code for JDK allowed Java
suddenly to become an acceptable
solution for limited abusin builders to
integrate with so while before opening
up the source code you could download
the JDK for Linux and install it
yourself now it's being bundled by the
distributions of of common Linux
distributed exactly and that's something
we have actually seen in the past six
months actually we've seen this from
beginning of the project so as soon as
the source code was available for
download they were already Gentoo
packages but in particularly particular
angular I mean the intro is always first
to go rather be sort of three-peat
exactly and they have it easy
to purely source good base but in the
past six months we actually seen a
massive increase in adoption among the
mainstream distribution so not just
fedora and Debbie and Debbie Ann but
also of course we're going to and
openSUSE and Mandriva and all the
distributions deriving from them so
given the way the distribution space
under linux is build up that means that
we have a certain trickle-down effect
that we're observing now yeah but this
it's sort of a little weird because I
mean as far as I understand sons open
sourcing strategy says open JDK will be
Java 7 but all these open JDK
distributions in the Linux space they
are all Java 6 open sourced so what's
the status anyway is it is it Java 6
that goes open or is it Java 7 or how
what about that right I think when the
original announcement was made to do
open JDK a lot of people underestimated
the need for an open six implementation
because from a distribution perspective
what you really want to provide your
users is a stable foundation to package
and vilification zone and where Java 7
is still in heavy development mode in
fact it will remain in that mode for
another year another year meaning end of
2009 exactly that's when I think
releases a plan or beginning of 2010 by
now that means that distributions didn't
want to really wait for 7/2 appears so
they wanted to have something to connect
to a ship today in 2008 and accordingly
what we did there was to try to figure
out a good way to go from the open JDK 7
code we had to provide an open JDK 6
implementation so to speak what we've
done there was to go back from the
future to the past effectively and
that's what open JDK 6 is that's an
implementation of SE 6 based on the JDK
7 source code that's cut down to just
the api's that are in 6 itself and that
source code has gone through
the distributions it's been actually
successfully ran through the
certification process by right hand who
have managed to build fully compatible
binaries of se6 and ran em through a TCK
suit the testitude for Java for Fedora 9
and that's something that other suitors
are currently trying to follow as well
so we are seeing how on one hand the
open JDK project provides a certain kind
of develop an environment for seven like
at the same time providing this
foundation for packaging and other
things distributions want to do through
the open JDK six project that has some
interesting side effects for example
that all of a sudden the richness of how
to put this on the Java open source and
free software ecosystem becomes really
attractive distributions to look at in
the package you could you could find
early attempts to package many libraries
before but now that the full se6
platform is there available as free
software in the code of solutions all of
a sudden it becomes much much easier to
actually package full-fledged
applications like say the NetBeans
editor or eclipse or JBoss or GlassFish
and at some point so as part of the
distribution
exactly and that's something that we're
now increasingly seeing as well as a
motivation for distributions to look at
ever expanding the set of packages Java
packages available for their users what
do you think or what what is happening
to the other implementations of the JVM
the non Sun implementations are they
affected by open sourcing I would say no
because most of them really are
concerned with specific products or
specific platforms so for example if you
look at some vendors implementation
that's actually JDK port to their own
platform then since some typically
doesn't sell say Zed series boxes there
is no such code you know
dedicates up yet so accordingly there is
nothing connected at the same time we're
seeing the community actually take
OpenJDK and pick up this like on that
and try to make it as ubiquitous as
possible so there are projects like zero
which tries to provide very how to put
this nicely maintainable backends for
the hotspot interpreter and the jet
compiler based on the low-level virtual
machine to platform supported by Lib FFI
and LVM which includes pretty much most
of those supported by GCC so we're
seeing people checking the open JDK
source code and porting it to two other
systems and trying to sort of explore
the boundaries of ubiquity and that's
great yeah that sounds really cool but
how did you actually get there how did
it work out to open source a closed
source I mean it's a huge project
it's huge code basically it's a huge
cultural step to take from being close
source to open sourcing how did sang go
about that and well how what were the
challenges how do you actually makes it
such a success the major challenge is
really to have access to good lawyers
and why is that why lawyers because you
really need to be sure that what you're
publishing actually is something you can
publish and typically proprietary
software development is such that you
buy components from outside for things
that are not your core expertise or that
you don't want to basically build up
course parties in so accordingly it's
very important to track third-party code
in your products and to be sure to
actually know that you can publish what
you have you have to make sure to Loras
code the contracts you have with others
you have to simplest negotiate rights
and all that and son has done a lot of
Lego footwork which is also part of why
son has open up JDK 7 rather than JDK 6
you just didn't want to do the legal
support the legal the legal park which
is really tricky that sort of taken care
of but still
there's many open-source processes that
don't sort of get off the ground
this seems to have happened for OpenJDK
and I believe there's more to that than
having good lawyers how did you write it
right what Sun also has are rather
clever people who've been involved with
this effort from from earlier on so Sun
has actually reached out to the open
source java community outside Sun back
in 2003 2004 timeframe even though Beck
vans Sun wasn't ready to open things up
yet they were still actively looking at
things we were doing around cafe and
classpath and gcj discussing approaches
with us how to make such a project fly
so once there were eight to go they were
able to integrate very nicely with the
existing community rather than trying to
build up their own from scratch and
that's part of the secret behind all of
the penetration so to say into
distributions that the people who've
been before working on projects around
the gnu classpath have been able to
actually embrace open JDK as a similar
project in scope and breadth and to
contribute to it and that took some
efforts on sun site to provide a
suitable environment instead of
adjudicate for such things that happen
and part of that is really based on the
efforts done in the past to actually
reach out that community and talk to
them what we've done there for example
one of I think the most important things
we ever done with all this was to
actually invite the Sun team to the
FOSDEM conference which is a free and
open source developer meeting in
Brussels which takes place each year in
February it hosts a lot of open source
projects that Mozilla guys are they have
ax guys go there and so on and we've
used this for the past five years as a
meeting point for the Java Libre
community in Europe and further where
people are working on their own virtual
machines would come together to talk
about ecologic approaches and talk about
packaging and such issues so by
accepting invitations to come and join
us some was able to actually tap into
the existing
rather than having to figure out how to
boost job its own and go through more
painful process and that does work
surprisingly well mm-hmm so embracing
the communities that are there wasn't
important to step on the way what would
you say where there are some some big
challenges dangers that you had to face
on the way some sort of interesting
adventure stories right there is there
is always something that pops up out of
nowhere I think the biggest adventure
really was for the Sun team to adopt
their culture in ways that allow them to
get more out of the collaboration with
community and that's a typical change
many Sun projects have to go through if
you look at the way open Solaris is
taking or the way GlassFish is taken or
if other similar projects have taken
coming from proprietary to open the
hardest bit is really the culture change
going from holy internal process for
developing self the one that actually
allows external contributors to plug
into as many places as possible that's a
road we're still on so opens you the
case by by no means finish when it comes
to for example infrastructure of
collaboration but that's something how
does it actually look at this sort of
adaptation what do you example of what
actually needs to happen there so for
example one thing that projects
typically struggle with is that they
have their own internal in-house
infrastructure so OpenJDK actually the
whole jdk itself was developed in-house
using team wear which is sons own
distributed version control system it
was built by Larry McCoy who later go to
fame was with bit deeper after he left
son and team were is apparently I
haven't used it a very nice system works
over NFS and all that but given its
proprietary nature it would have been
less than useful for Axela contributors
to use outside son
not to mention the hole in the fest
thing so while such a tool is actually
useful in an internal context as soon as
one has to go open source one needs to
figure out ways that allow external
developers to plug in existing processes
so for example one of first things son
did was to think about a transition away
from from team where for JDK development
so accordingly we went we did a bit of a
three jump there from team where to
subversion for externally viewable
repositories and then after a certain
adaption face to read-only mercurial and
we picked mercurial because it seemed to
match very nicely both into existing
processes among developers at son as
well as into the ways the community
wanted to work with the code and from
read-only mica repositories to writable
and then to community access so that no
we actually have committees from outside
son who have commit access to the
codebase different branches of it
speaking of committees outside son how
is the developer community actually
structured how many commuters are there
and how many of them are son I don't
actually have an exact count but I would
say they're around two thousand
commuters outside son participating in
different porting projects and different
extensions as well as committing abuses
to the core libraries for example that's
amazing you say mm that's a huge
approach sorry - I said mm mm okay I see
yeah sorry
we just had last April with the eval
commit access so I think 2000 is fair
for eight months but we are most working
on on that and we always try to attract
new projects into the community mm-hm
how is it structures how our decisions
made in this in this project since
OpenJDK has been created with different
audiences in mind we didn't want to
prescribe a specific process to each
project so the
when JDK project itself is made up from
different sub projects there is one sub
project for JDK 7 there is one sub
project for open JDK 6-4 example porting
sub projects like the porting approach
to the mix platform the porting approach
to the high co platform then there are
feature projects like say the closures
project and many of these projects have
are led by some employees of course but
many aren't so about a half is not led
by some employees accordingly those
projects have very different goals some
of them are more exploratory others are
more academic in terms of what are
trying to achieve while others are very
straightforward in what are trying to do
with open JDK itself and we didn't want
to impose a specific structure under
these very different audiences because
for example if you're interested in
language extensions then your workflow
is probably gonna be a slightly
different from somebody who's interested
in taking open JDK as it is and just
making small tweaks to make it work on
the bsd platforms accordingly most
projects are rather autonomous of course
that means for the ones led by son
employees they do have their own
management chain of course about the
team leads but who decides which
projects are led by whom I mean many
open-source projects have sort of some
sort of democracy meritocracy or some
skip strict control or who decides how
is it designed how can it evolve who
actually leads the sub projects so the
jelly capes our project for example are
led by son Anders but at the same time
other projects created by the community
are not led by son in general so what
typically happens is that somebody would
propose for example a 2d rendering
pipeline for Linux yeah and they will
get to leave that project and we would
set up their project repositories they
would get committer access and they
would be able to as long as everything
is a right manage to prop the project
most autonomously
there are some small tweaks that we need
to work with for example we need to have
a corporate assignment to be able to
actually use the code and code bases to
ship to the JDK licenses because we
don't want to have different code bases
for say proprietor JDK and the
proprietary one but beside that
basically such projects evolve on their
own the interesting part happens when
such projects are merged into the main
code base we haven't had such a such a
thing yet because JDK 7 is still in
development but from last week's dev ox
conference from the announcements in his
keynote Mark Reinhold the lead engineer
on Java SE and open JDK mate it's clear
that Sun actually wants to have
community contributed features as part
of JDK 7 itself and those would be for
example this Java 2d extended pipeline
for Linux systems and for example the
implementation of jsr 308 which allows
for annotations on types improve static
checking abilities but let's say um or
let's let's take a look at the actual
let's say hot spot I would expect that
Sun wants to sort of keep control of hot
spot not give it away how is that
managed is there some sort of Sun
Oversight Committee who assigned the
approach sub project and project leads
or how is it actually managed who
decides who leads what so the way for
example the hot spot project works is
that the patch is coming into it or
reviewed regardless whether they come
from Sun or outside Sun and if those
patches best most are they go in
otherwise they don't
the initial seeding
right the initial settings of the
projects was done by science elf so
initially on the jdk itself it was
pretty much all sun committers it's all
and those projects can decide which new
members they accept and commit says in
America
sorry you know married
patek way so the way it works is that
the projects are organized in groups and
those groups have members and those
members can decide which you member
stillinger to introduce into a group so
when a member when when a new member is
proposed there is a vote among the
group's members and that way the
membership gets expanded and so far home
run it could happen that son employees
become the minority of committers and
some sort of really loses control or
gives up control of of the jdk control
is always a function of the amount of
work one does but yes that's technically
it's possible I don't think given that
we're invested so much that some would
ever actually invest less in the
platform itself but yes the the
mechanism projects allow for such a such
a gradual takeover to happen and that's
a good thing yeah I was just wondering
if son was had the courage to actually
do that it sounds like that which i
think is a good thing right I mean it's
it's in governance of the project of
course it's less a matter of courage but
one of finding people who are able to
expand things in in those areas hotspot
for example itself is a very technical
piece of C++ code that scares Java
developers away so let's say I'm a C++
geek and I'm interested in Java and I'd
like to contribute and become a
committer how do I go about that you
start off by signing patches so the
easiest way to do it is to actually pick
one of the projects on the open JDK site
depending on the area of expertise for
example hot spot and then to get in
touch with the corresponding mailing
list to discuss your ideas and your
proposals for changes and typically the
developers on say the hospitalist
are fresh appreciate good ideas and
maybe silent about bad ones but
typically conversation occurs and you
will be asked to back up your ideas with
patches eventually then your patches go
through a review process where they
typically get better over time
and once the reviewers are happy your
patch goes in if you keep contributing
good patches and eventually the overhead
of just manually reviewing your stuff
and then filling with the bug tracker
for all this become so high that
everybody just wants to give you commit
rights and to make you a member of the
group and that's how some of the group's
so far I've actually started to
incorporate members outside Sun for
example the co library's group has some
as well as the I think in is the new
translation group where new projects are
created and a new things are happening
in particular driven for example by
employees of companies outside sign
mm-hmm one of the trends that's been
going on for a while now is that the JVM
is becoming a platform for many
languages apart from Java itself and I
believe that open sourcing the JVM would
sort of have a positive effect on the
adoption of the JVM as a platform for
other languages what's going on there I
think that's the opposite true and I
think that might have been one of the
side motivations to do it because Bank
in the early days the JVM still was
pretty good performance wise it only got
better since of course but they can be
back in the early days it was still
pretty attractive and there is a guy who
maintains a webpage with more than 200
languages for the JVM a lot of those
actually came up in during the 90s and
early 2000s but for a lot of mainstream
languages successful platforms like
Python and Ruby the JVM wasn't such a
hot up ssin because it was seen as
proprietary and nobody really wanted to
tie the platform down to proprietary
foundation that's part of the problem
that say projects implementing such
languages on top of the CLR seem to have
sometimes in terms of community adoption
so going open sources actually change
the equation there significantly because
all of a sudden the JVM doesn't no
longer have this roadblock to adoption
and
accordingly we're seeing a lot of
interest from other communities to
experiment with it and to try to not
just create toy project but also have
actually fully working environments for
mainstream languages working as fast or
even faster than they would be in the
regular world in SeaWorld on top of the
JVM like the JRuby guys have done where
their performance is actually comparable
to the latest experimental performance
of Ruby interpreters and beats the one
of the current stable series Wow
according to some blogs
so just repeating with when bloggers say
if it's an it's gotta be true pay for
for reporting stuff that's not really
out yet yeah but yes we're seeing that
for example the JVM is is becoming
attracted to Poland platform for the
Ruby community because on one hand your
Vegas application still runs as it runs
on the regular race installation on the
other hand you get all the benefits from
opening up to JDK for free basically
so whatever further investments are made
in the JVM to for example make
multi-core support better in future
releases or further performance
improvements the JVM gets them for free
because it is so important on the
service side where time is money so
accordingly everybody's selling servers
and everybody's selling safe operating
systems and everybody's selling
large-scale plication servers has a
vested interest in making the JVM go as
fast as possible and yeah we're seeing
that we're also seeing an explosion in
languages up with the JVM so the past
two three years have seen a lot of
exploration for example in the
functional language domain for example
in say a new Lisp implementations on top
of the JVM besides the traditional
targets so it's a very exciting time to
actually be a JVM developer and part of
that is that the JVM itself is now being
considered
for modification to make it more
suitable for dynamic languages as the
name itself says the DJ stands for Java
it's been somewhat so actually so
actually there's feedback from other
languages who'd like to move to the JVM
and they say we'd like to do this but we
need this feature and that that's reason
enough for the feature to be
incorporated into the JVM exactly so
it's actually what we have there is a
project in we're gonna open JDK
it's called multi language VM now of
course that doesn't mean that the JVM
gets translated into other languages
Spanish or something like that that's
why we came up with a different name the
vinci vm because of this renaissance in
programming languages so these guys are
working on extending the JVM to make it
more suitable for example for Ruby and
Python senior languages and they're
working very closely together with
implemented implementers of the JVM base
implementations to make sure they meet
their requirements so as one of the
things lated was to have a developer
meeting this autumn in Santa Clara
California where they invited for
example developers of closure and jython
and even parrots what errand parrot is
actually a Perl 6 virtual machine ok to
discuss what kind of difference
different requirements they exist in
different languages to make them run
very well on top of the JVM itself and
from all the impressions I get from
talking to the people involved that was
massive success and son is trying to
actually push the JVM towards evolving
to supporting such languages you can
even better in the future as there is
this runtime gap that I was speaking up
before where JVM has pretty much the
best free software runtime excuse me
environment out there has a lot to offer
in terms of performance in terms of
tooling in terms of the ecosystem around
to two other languages what's the big
deal about incorporating requirements
from other languages why not just add
them why not just add other byte codes
and make everyone happy well
what you want to do is really to make
sure that you implement extensions
carefully the JVM is a beast that has
been out there for at least ten years
and there's a lot of byte code written
for the JVM so accordingly any changes
down to this ecosystem have to be
weighed very careful against the
benefits weigh careful against the
drawbacks and the drawback of adding is
you need to be backwards compatible but
adding on new byte codes doesn't seem to
be such a big deal the drawback of
adding new byte codes is that it needs
to be very very careful to make sure
that the static verification properties
of a JVM don't break because one of the
often overseen advantages of the JVM
architecture is it actually comes with a
verifier built-in which allows you to
which allows use of certain kind of
security properties on the bad code
itself to analyze those and approve
those and accordingly what you don't
want to have is you don't want to throw
security away to make a certain language
run faster so what you're trying to do
are explore ways to create such
extensions to the JVM see how well those
work or in practice see how what effects
actually have a specifications and if
they work out if they're performing
enough if they don't break anything then
to add them to the jegging specification
itself and that's what this DaVinci
project does basically it's and it's a
playground to certain certain degree to
try out different extension ideas and
see how well they work in practice and
so far one of the things that's been
plumeria bear has been the so-called
invokedynamic
pseudo instruction that's a hack
basically to allow the JVM to export
some of the underlying method linkage
functionality to different languages
because typically the problem when
you're creating a a language of the JVM
is that you want to call your own
functions or classes or methods and then
you end up bumping hard against big
in byte codes in Java which are all
rather tied to Java semantics because
they have to invoke Java methods right
so you have to check the types according
yeah and what this extension is trying
to do is actually to decouple that a bit
more and to allow the hotspot which by
itself is a certain rather dynamic
properties to link code and to be able
to optimize in the optimize at one time
to allow those facilities to be exported
to userland codes or to to Co diplomat
new languages and to make it possible
for such code to actually invoke its own
functions and methods in ways that don't
have to clash with Java semantics and
will make them a lot more efficient
because then such calls become as
efficient as reflection yesterday
without having to actually go to
reflection and caching mm-hmm okay so
there's this balance that needs to be
kept between the different groups I I
see that now yeah what what were the
requirements of other open-source
projects to actually adopt the JVM I
mean what about open source languages
you said obviously performance is one
big issue and then the license are there
other things that needed to happen sort
of cultural gaps that need to be bridged
or are there any stories about the sort
of different open source cultures that
got and get in touch with the focus of
the JVM I think it's it's typical that
you have some people blazing trail there
and one of the trailblazers inside Sun
was Tim Bray who already back in the
2004 time frame organized the first
meeting of people implementing languages
of the JVM is a small summit which
included Larry wall from the Perl
community and Ito from the Python
community who begged then discussed ways
to actually make those things work out
the real trailblazers who made the JVM
popular as a platform I think where the
JRuby guys who picked up the JRuby
projects before sliding doormat a couple
of years ago first among them was
charles nutter
who now also works at sun and who picked
up a project and try to get it to a
point where it could actually run rails
and I could actually run typical Ruby
applications and in doing so they've
actually brought in a lot of fresh fresh
air into the whole debate around
languages of the JTA and they show that
it's actually possible with sufficient
effort to create implementation that
really performant that the JVM wasn't
just for Java which was not a culture
gap I think on both sides
that showed that actually it's possible
to not just have a toy implementation
but the actual permutations that are
comparable to existing ones so in many
ways the JRuby team has I think acted as
a as a bridge builder to other
communities and has blazed a path
forward accordingly they also working
very closely together with the DaVinci
project and have for example I think
blaze the way is that Sun for the jaikon
project to become part of what Sun does
and you can see this now not just on the
JVM side but also on the tooling side
where for example the NetBeans project
is now trying to turn into an IDE that's
not just for Java anymore but also for
say PHP and for Python and Perl Ruby and
such languages so in a certain way the
Java community has gone from being very
inward looking five years ago to a
community it's been playing quite a bit
with other languages and it's trying to
figure out ways to interoperate with
those and it's trying to across the
fence and to make those fences go away
as much as possible so that's been one
of the I think very very nice
developments of the past couple of years
mm-hmm
what about the operating system side
especially for open source systems bsd
linux um was there also a gap that
needed to be bridged some some sort of
crust building things or some cultural
things that need to be done
in order to get acceptance or were they
so interested in getting the JDK as part
of the distros that it worked out
basically itself it was actually quite
different between the bsd world and
linux world in the bsd world what we had
there was porting projects like diablo
who've been working on sons proprietary
code base for a while and had resulted
and certified as compatible releases of
java 1.5 i think which is available from
the freebsd foundation as a download so
the bsd community was already working
with sons proprietary source code bases
which was available under
correspondingly open enough licenses for
them to do that so on their side the
change wasn't such a big one on the
Linux side though the project doing that
was the black down project the black
down project slightly went to sleep a
couple of years ago once sunset reported
supporting Linux with his own binaries
so on Linux side there was this gap
where there wasn't much going on in
terms of porting and working with jdk
source code itself accordingly
um son had to do some trust-building
there and that's what we did basically
by including sun then from the other
side and into these foster meetings and
making sure they actually talked with
the people o who planned to work with
the source code once it's open on the
other hand it also means that once the
linux guys were all happy and set and
had their source code bundles and it was
all GPL and free and included for the
bsd guys were still sitting on their all
proprietary downloads so what they
wanted to do was of course to be able to
play along with that so one of the
things we did in the past couple of
months was to create a way for the bsd
source code base to migrate into open
JDK itself which involved again talking
with very good lawyers fortunately it
was quick and reasonably painless and
now we actually have a BSD porting
project inside open JDK
which
also includes soy latte a port to macosx
so that's one of the benefits say for
the bsd community in particular for the
guys using apple notebooks that wasn't
so obvious in the beginning to actually
be able to play with jdk seven wives
being developed and try all those things
by merging different branches of
different projects of doing projects so
and we're just seeing that we're seeing
people who are trying to for example use
and contribute to the da vinci BM on mac
OS x who then go and take the source
code from the bsd port and work on it
until they make it all work and compile
and fly for them which is great that's
just the power of open source a thing
that it allows such people to actually
get things done where they would be
stuck otherwise yeah on a different vein
how do you actually assign features in
an open source project like the open JDK
I mean it's sort of more fun to develop
new cool features and you said something
about the 2d rendering engine for Linux
can well imagine that people are
interested in implementing a new 2d 2d
rendering engine but how do you actually
get people to fix bugs that are reported
and that are voted high on the backtrack
and that kind of stuff the best way to
do is to actually pay them to fix it
actually son employees people think just
that okay it sorry III can see that but
it's actually true that the unpaid non
son members get to do all the cool stuff
where all the paid son employees to dig
through the dirt and bugs
no no so we actually saying all the
people come up and contribute bug fixes
to open JDK from resulting from their
typical grievances so if if you look at
different mailing lists you will often
see people coming up and saying well
I've seen this bug on the home the Sun
bug tracker which is on box some com
and it's been bothering me for the past
two years is anybody working on this and
since Java is so popular and since we
get so many bug reports unfortunately we
just can't fix all of them so sometimes
you will find that we're not working on
a bug after you asked for it and then
typically we find that people are
sufficiently interested in fixing the
bug for themselves if it's bugging them
that hard but they will contribute a
patch for it that's one part of it the
other part is people who are working
with JDK codebase internally who then
discover issues and then contribute
fixes for them too so we're seeing a
certain amount of bug fixes come from
community and it really depends on which
community it is for the Lunas community
for example a lot of bug fixing happens
around say compiler issues because they
typically the first ones to discover
some GCC compiler issue because
typically on the latest latest revision
of those whereas say the windows people
aren't if they use GCC it alright yeah
so so typically the Linux community will
have many many regular fixes for GCC
issues coming up from them other
companies or communities would have
fixes for areas where they interested in
whereas on the Sun side the project
itself is of course governed by what
interests we have in doing things so for
our engineers we certainly set our own
goals for JDK 7 quite a bit of features
in there are things some needs to do to
make the platform better there have been
on a list for a long time but they can
also be features we have to do for a
customer to where customers are coming
to someone saying well we actually need
to have support for say some secure
transport layer or things like that in
the next release and then we're looking
for those and basically pay people to do
them what's much easier for the
community outside sound though is of
course to think about their own features
like to provide and we can't really say
that we're gonna take each one of those
into Jetta kid selling itself but I
think the inclusion or the targeted
inclusion of the Java 2d extender
pipeline and Jase are 308 shows that
it's possible to actually get major
features in through the community in
today's release some of those features
are of course harder than others so if
you for example want extend the Java
language you will find yourself
struggling against a lot of things one
of those being the language
specification and having to evaluate the
impact such a change has the language
spec itself whereas other areas like say
that the 2d rendering pipeline are more
self constrained and so the impact on
other areas of the system is not that
huge and while I'm speaking about
language changes what we are going to
have for JDK 7 is going to be a project
inside open JDK to actually collect
proposals and ideas and code in
particular for small language changes
for small extensions to the compiled
language itself because there are a lot
of small ideas with not a lot of impact
it would be still nice to have and
that's one of the areas I think Joe
Darcy who's also running open JDK 6
project is going to focus on the next
year and then but also have to have the
big migration of the changes that were
done in the 6 update 10 release train
onto 7 and so on and so on so work is
never over but how do you get people to
focus on a release date even to commit
to a release date it's I mean unless you
said set a deadline actually get people
to sort of tie the sec they'll go on
forever and ever without integrating
ever so what's the overall governance of
the project and how do you get
volunteers to commit and work within
such a frame that's a good question and
we actually haven't really quite been
there yet because we haven't actually
released seven
I think we're gonna see some
experimentation around that all right so
you have some estimates of when release
seven will be out so it appears that
some thought has been given to that
right so last week at the devas
conference in his keynote mark ronald
mentioned early 2010 which gives us
about a year from now to actually get
necessary changes in turns how is it
managed I mean how do you get the non
employees that the unpaid people to
commit this kind to this kind of date
how do you get them to focus by
communicating by communicating a lot
about goals and release criteria and
stuff like that and for example there
are some changes from the community that
would be nice to have where we're not
sure if they're going to be ready in the
timeframe 37 is this some sort of
staging process before the release some
let's say feature freezes half of you
before that and so this kind of stepwise
stabilizing yes on the Sun side
definitely and I think that's also gonna
be driving what further features make it
into seven from outside Sun but I can't
give you any any dates or details on
that yet because we're still working out
those parts of the seven process which
is why the question is somewhat hard to
answer right now is we haven't released
yet we still have some experimentation
to do around this what the best way is
to actually make this work in the logic
on Icee Icee
yeah that's cool thank you very much is
there something you'd like to add some
particularly interesting stories you'd
like to tell or something you feel we
haven't covered yet which is definitely
we're saying all on my side I'd just
like to mention that we have this fun
conference coming up again in February
this year so it's gonna be fasting again
we will have this Java developer room
for dinner and we've used this in the
past as the Java leader meeting in
Europe we have expanded this now include
the Sun guys and we're looking to expand
this to include more of the Java
communities so if your listeners are
interested in actually coming over to
the Boston conference which is free and
it's a great beer bash basically in the
wintery chile brussels
it's on the 7th 8th of february at real
be at the for university of brussels so
that's when you'll be able to see you
there but this episode probably won't be
on the air before the conference no
worries then then I think that's all
from my side and I'm really happy to
have had a chance to talk about the
project okay well thank you much for
taking the time and thanks everybody for
listening thanks thanks for downloading
and listening to software engineering
Radio soft engineering radio is an
educational program brought to you by
hillside Europe if you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes visit our website and
s/ii - radio dot length if you want to
support us you can donate to the AC
radio team via the website or you can
advertise for us radio for example by
clicking on the Digg reddit delicious
and slash dot buttons to contact the
team please send email to team at s e -
radio net or if it is specific to an
episode please use the comments facility
on the website so other people can react
to your comments this episode of se
radio as well as all other episodes are
licensed under creative commons 2.5
license please see the website for
details thanks to Charlie Crowell and
the positive music network of the music
used in the show the song is called
Vegas hard rock shuffle
[Music]
you